Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. We begin today our last פרק,
Perek, last week of כתובות. Ketubot. And we start at the very
bottom, it's today's דף Daf is קפה Kuf Hey 105. We start
at the very, very bottom of קד עמוד ב. Kuf Daled Amud
Bet. שני דייני. Shne Dayane. So let's take a look.
שני דייני גזירות, Shne dayane gzerot, two judges who made decrees, which
is interesting, we'll see what that means.
Right? What?
Didn't you see the introduction to the משנה?
Mishnah? Right. היו בירושלים, Hayu beYerushalayim, were in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, אדמון וחנן
בן אבישלום. Admon veChanan ben Avishalom. אדמון Admon and חנן בן אבישלום.
Chanan ben Avishalom. חנן אמר שני דברים אדמון אמר שבעה. Chanan amar
shne devarim Admon amar shiva. חנן Chanan said two things, more than
two things hopefully, but רש״י Rashi says that two things that he
was like known for that he did that the Sages did not
agree with him, and אדמון Admon said seven. And we are going
to and you'll see that obviously the first one here is going
to tie into the themes of כתובות. Ketubot. Some of the others
will be related to כתובות, Ketubot, some will not, but we're bringing
in all of the sets of the things that they said because
of the original hook here.
And number one is, מי שהלך למדינת הים ואשתו תובעת מזונות. Mi
shehalach limdinat hayam veishto tova mezonot. Somebody went to overseas and his
wife demands to be fed, right and demands her support, and the
husband isn't around. So obviously she has to be able to put
food on the table, but the concern is that he's not around
to defend himself, and maybe he already prepaid it or something. So
חנן אומר, Chanan omer, חנן Chanan says, תשבע בסוף ולא תשבע בתחילה.
Tishava basof velo tishava batchila.
She'll take an oath at the end, but not at the beginning.
What's the end? רש״י Rashi says the end is that
if
eventually he doesn't return because he dies, and then she wants to
collect her whole כתובה, Ketubah,
then she'll take the normal oath that a woman takes when she
collects her כתובה, Ketubah, and at that time she'll also basically swear
that she did not, you know, that there's no outstanding moneys that
she had already collected, that she's owed the full amount and so
on, and that'll cover for anything that she had collected when she
was getting paid for the food, you know, the possibility that anything
had already been prepaid at that stage. Of course, if he doesn't
die in the end, it's not exactly clear. Maybe she'll take an
oath when he finally returns or whatever after all the collecting is
done, or maybe when he returns he'll have a chance to defend
himself, and then if and then we'll just sort of follow his
lead at that moment. Okay, but that the oath will be at
the end, not at the beginning. נחלקו עליו בני כהנים גדולים. Nechlaku
alav bne kohanim gdolim.
The sons of the כהנים גדולים. Kohanim Gdolim. It's a, yeah, it's
a fact, meaning that whole group of בני כהנים גדולים. Bne kohanim
gdolim. How many כהנים גדולים Kohanim Gdolim did you have? I guess
maybe they had a lot of kids. I mean, it was the
time of בית שני, Bayit Sheni, so okay, there was a big
turnover of כהנים גדולים. Kohanim Gdolim. But it's funny that they have
like a identity and a voice in הלכה Halakha here. תשבע בתחילה
ובסוף. Tishava batchila uvasof. No, she has to take an oath at
the beginning and at the end. אמר רבי דוסא בן הורכינס כדבריהם.
Amar Rabbi Dosa ben Horkinas kidvreihem. And רבי דוסא בן הורכינס Rabbi
Dosa ben Horkinas ruled like them. So he says that they have
to take an oath at the beginning when she comes to collect
מזונות, Mezonot, and then later if she's coming to collect basic כתובה.
Ketuva. ואמר רבי יוחנן בן זכאי יפה אמר חנן, Veamar Rabbi Yochanan
ben Zakkai yafe amar Chanan, no
he actually sides with חנן. Chanan. לא תשבע אלא בסוף, Lo tishava
ela basof, the oath should be only at the end, not at
the beginning when she's coming to collect מזונות, Mezonot, but only possibly
only at the end if he's dead and when she's coming to
collect her כתובה. Ketubah. Okay, so before the גמרא Gemara today, just
to warn you, is not going to discuss this debate at all,
this כתובה Ketubah thing. It's going to really just focus on the
first phrase here of שני דייני גזירות Shne dayane gzerot and talk
to us a little bit about people's roles as דיינים Dayanim and
so on. So before we get into that גמרא, Gemara, which once
again we're going to be focusing more on sort of the opening
of the משנה, Mishnah, I thought I'd point to you the interesting
little תוספות Tosafot here on קד עמוד ב. Kuf Daled Amud Bet.
שני דייני גזירות היו בירושלים אדמון וחנן בן אבישלום. Shne dayane gzerot
hayu beYerushalayim Admon veChanan ben Avishalom. So תוספות Tosafot says, הכי גרס
רבינו תם, Hachi gares Rabbeinu Tam, אבישלום Avishalom as opposed to אבשלום.
Avshalom. דהא רבי מאיר אמר פרק חלק דאבשלום אין לו חלק לעולם
הבא היכי מסקינן בשמיה? Deha Rabbi Meir amar perek chelek deAvshalom ein
lo chelek leolam haba heichi maskinan bishmei? How would you name anybody
אבשלום Avshalom if אבשלום Avshalom doesn't have a portion in the עולם
הבא? Olam Haba? So maybe he was named after a different אבשלום,
Avshalom, who says it was named after, you know, דוד's David son
אבשלום? Avshalom? But anyway, he wants to insist that the name is
אבישלום Avishalom and he goes on with that whole long discussion about
that, where he never at anywhere says how could we have a
תנא Tanna by the name of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael if ישמעאל
Yishmael in rabbinic literature is supposed to be a רשע, Rasha,
you know, anyway, I don't know. Also who says it's the same,
who says it's after that person? I mean, it's just the same
name having nothing to do with that particular person.
Like modern Hebrew names like נמרוד. Nimrod.
Exactly, exactly. So anyway, I thought I'd just bring your attention to
that תוספות. Tosafot. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Yes,
the question?
I mean, is it usual that you have a מחלוקת Machloket and
then someone says, like, oh no, I agree with the first guy?
I mean, he's not necessarily adding anything, right? You'd say?
Well, except that רבי יוחנן בן זכאי's Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai a
pretty weighty authority to
back up your, you know.
All right. No, yeah, but no, so when the גמרא Gemara has
another opinion that just echoes the first but it's stated as an
independent opinion, then the גמרא Gemara wants to understand how it's different
than the earlier one. Here, clearly there's a question of picking sides,
so it's not you don't have to make רבי יוחנן בן זכאי
Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai a חידוש, Chidush, he's just picking sides. Okay,
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. ורמינהי, Uremini, I'll
ask you on this.
שלושה... Shlosha... We have a ברייתא braita that doesn't say דייני גזירות,
Dayanei Gezeirot,
judges who made edicts, but דייני גזילות, Dayanei Gezeilot, judges who ruled
over issues of theft, and in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and it says three
instead of
two: אדמון בן גדאי, Admon ben Gadai, וחנן המצרי, v'Chanan Hamitzri, חנן
Chanan the Egyptian, וחנן בן אבישלום. v'Chanan ben Avishalom. So basically, you've
got one extra guy here, this חנן המצרי, Chanan Hamitzri, and it's
this דייני גזילות, Dayanei Gezeilot, not דייני גזירות. Dayanei Gezeirot. So the
גמרא Gemara says קשיא תלתא אבתרי קשיא גזירות אגזילות. kashya tlata atrei,
kashya gezeirot agezeilot. So this has three, that has two; this has
גזילות, gezeilot, this has גזירות. gezeirot. So it also says, of course,
you could have asked, said that they answer one another. There were
two of them that were דייני גזירות, Dayanei Gezeirot, and then חנן
Chanan and, what's his name? and, who was the other one? חנן
Chanan and אדמון Admon were also דייני גזילות Dayanei Gezeilot with this
third guy, so they were doing double tasks, right? So yes, there
were two דייני גזירות, Dayanei Gezeirot, and then there were three דייני
גזילות. Dayanei Gezeilot. But it doesn't sound like that. It sounds like
we're all, like, they're variations of the same story. So what's the
story? Is it גזירות gezeirot or is it גזילות? gezeilot? Is it
two or is it three? So the גמרא Gemara says thank you.
It says, so the גמרא Gemara says, בשלמא תלתא אבתרי לא קשיא.
bishlama tlata atrei lo kashya. The fact that in our משנה mishna
it mentions two and in the ברייתא braita it mentions three, that's
not difficult. דחשיב ליה קתני דלא חשיב ליה לא קתני. dechashiv lei
katani, delo chashiv lei lo kutani. It mentions the ones that are
weighty and important, not the ones that are not as weighty. So
it mentions the two most important, אדמון Admon and חנן. Chanan. It
did not mention the third one, this חנן המצרי. Chanan Hamitzri. Number
one. Number two is, דלא חשיב ליה לא קתני אלא גזירות אגזילות
קשיא. delo chashiv lei lo katani, ela gezeirot agezeilot kashya. But how
are you going to reconcile that in our משנה mishna they're referred
to דייני גזירות Dayanei Gezeirot and in the ברייתא braita דייני גזילות?
Dayanei Gezeilot? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק
שהיו גוזרים גזירות על גזילות. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, shehayu gozrim
gezeirot al gezeilot. Okay, they,
what they would do is they would make rulings and edicts related
to matters of theft. So according to some, they would be referred
to as דייני גזירות, Dayanei Gezeirot, others as דייני גזילות. Dayanei Gezeilot.
כדתניא, kid'tanya, we're going to see. כדתניא, kid'tanya, like we have in
the ברייתא. braita. Exact, exact, exact. That's the new גזירה gezeirah today,
no stealing.
What kind of name is that, אדמון? Admon? What is that, humanity?
I don't know. I thought it had to do with red. Anyway,
anyway, כדתניא קטמה נטיעה. kid'tanya, kitema netiah.
If an animal goes into, into the neighbor's yard and, basically, you
know, plucks, you know, eats away, nibbles away at the young shoots
and the young plantings. רבי יוסי אומר גוזרי גזירות שבירושלים, Rabbi Yosei
omer, gozrei gezeirot she'bi'Yerushalayim, and now you see why it made the
connection, גוזרי גזירות, gozrei gezeirot, those who make edicts in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
אומרים נטיעה בת שנתה שתי כסף, omrim netiah bat shnata shtei kessef,
if it's a one-year-old plant, then we just, you know, assign a
fixed value of it as two silver coins. בת שתי שנים ארבע
כסף, bat shtei shanim arba kessef, if it's a two-year-old planting, four.
So anyway, this is interesting because, so that's how it allows the
conflation here. Here we have an explicit ברייתא braita about גוזרי גזירות
gozrei gezeirot and it's talking about an injury that we might not
call גזל, gezel, we might call נזק, nezek, but you know, נזק
nezek is a form of injury and theft of another person, not
willful, but you know, due to negligence. So that allows us to
conflate the phrase of גזירות gezeirot and גזילות. gezeilot. But what's also
interesting is as opposed to the way we normally identify this idea
of גזירה, gezeirah, a גזירה gezeirah is like, you know, I don't
know, don't read by the candlelight, you'll come to tip it. You
know, something like that. It's a safeguard. Don't do this lest you
come to do something else. And here we rule that it's more
about just, you know, making sort of legal rulings
and basically, you know, creating basic like rules about here's what we're
going to assign as a fixed value for this type of a
damage. You see here it's called a גזירה gezeirah as well, which
makes also sense. Because why would you call them דייני גזירות? Dayanei
Gezeirot? Like we imagine that גזירות gezeirot in terms of, like, general
practices of, like, rabbinic law are things that come through at least
some larger consensus of the רבנים, rabbanim, even if one person dreamt
them up, presumably, you know, it's an issue that emerges from a
type of a consensus. But here דייני גזירות, Dayanei Gezeirot, you imagine
like, here are these judges, you know, they're doing their function as
judges and they're making these edicts. Well, who are they making the
edicts for? Like how do, you know, what type of a גזירה
gezeirah are they making? So it means like, if you sort of
see them as supervising, you know, monetary matters, they're like civil judges
and they're supervising monetary matters and they're establishing certain parameters, you know,
in terms of how they're going to fine certain things and what's
going to be the punishments for certain things and so on, then
it fits that a concept of דייני גזירות. Dayanei Gezeirot. So that
seems to be and דיינים dayanim also, which is very much in
the sense of really judging and dealing with real cases and applying
the law to real cases. Yes.
But what I find even more interesting is it sort of gives
a background, I mean we don't usually have it. Like, you know,
alright, the כתובה ketubah for אלמנה almanah is this, the כתובה ketובה
for בתולה betulah is this, but here's saying, oh look, this is
what these guys did.
Well, that's what I said to you, we're going to see in
the rest of the פרק perek that we're going to use this
as a hook to discuss a lot of statements that they said,
some relating to כתובות, ketubot, some not. So sometimes you have that.
Sometimes the משניות mishnayot have collections and they want to bring those
collections in and there's not a way, they're not going to chop
it up to make it connect to the particular theme of every
location. For example, all the אין בין. ein bein. אין בין, ein
bein, you know, ראש השנה ליום כיפור, Rosh Hashana l'Yom Kippur, and
אין בין, ein bein, you know, שבת ליום טוב, Shabbos l'Yom Tov,
אין בין ein bein this, אין בין ein bein this, אין בין
ein bein that. There's not one מסכת. masechet. that belongs to, so
it belongs to, so you find a hook and then you teach
the whole package. So that's what's going to be
happening, and this is
why they're saying there were. Yeah, exactly, so we're going to have
a package of things that come from these two דיינים Dayanim that
they said distinctive rulings and we're bringing it in here at the
end of כתובות. Ketubot. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay, רמינהי, Ramini, I'll ask on this. שלשה דייני גזירות היו בירושלים,
Shelosha Dayanei Gezerot hayu biYerushalayim, there were three: אדמון וחנן ונחום. Admon
veChanan veNachum.
So now we get a third one that we hadn't mentioned before
by the name of נחום. Nachum. So what's that story? So אמר
רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, מאן תנא נחום, Man tanna Nachum, who
teaches that נחום Nachum is from those of that group? רב נתן
היא, Rav Natan hi, דתניא רב נתן אומר, De-tanya Rav Natan omer,
we're talking about a ברייתא, Baraita, רב נתן אומר, Rav Natan omer,
אף נחום המדי מגוזרי גזירות שבירושלים היה. Af Nachum HaMadai mi-gozrei gezerot
she-biYerushalayim haya. Right,
so we all know about נחום המדי Nachum HaMadai because every שבת
Shabbos we say במה מדליקין, Bameh Madlikin, right?
So even נחום המדי Nachum HaMadai is amongst the גוזרי גזירות
היה, gozrei gezerot haya, ולא הודו לו חכמים, velo hodu lo Chachamim,
the sages didn't agree with him. Like, it's so funny, like, what
are we debating history? We're debating a point. Presumably, he played some
role, there was a question like how much was he in, a
certain type of capacity or another. Obviously, he dealt with cases or
nobody would have thought it, but did he have this official status
of גוזרי גזירות, gozrei gezerot, that seems to be the debate. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, ותו
ליכא אלא הני, Vetu lika ela hani, do
you know no more than those three? והאמר רב פנחס אמר רב
אושעיא, Ve-ha-amar Rav Pinchas amar Rav Oshaya, שלש מאות ותשעים וארבעה, Shelosh
me'ot tishim ve-arba'ah, 394 בתי
דינים
שהיו בירושלים,
batei dinim she-hayu
biYerushalayim, there were, there were courts in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, pretty hard to
imagine. 300 is usually an exaggeration, I don't know exactly what to
do with the 94 number. Yeah, I don't know. Anyway, היו בירושלים,
hayu biYerushalayim, כנגדם בתי כנסיות kenegdam batei knesiyot and just as many
synagogues, וכנגדם בתי מדרשות ve-kenegdam batei midrashot and just as many study
halls.
And so a very strange רש"י Rashi by the way, I'll show
you. רש"י Rashi says, so first the first רש"י Rashi isn't so
strange, like two lines down רש"י Rashi says on the narrow lines,
בתי דינים של עשרים ושלשה, Batei Dinim shel esrim u-shelosha,
so major courts, courts of 23, not just little courts of three.
There were 394. Then רש"י Rashi says בתי כנסיות להתפלל, batei knesiyot
le-hitpalel, בתי מדרשות למשנה ולתלמוד. batei midrashot le-mishna u-le-talmud.
Like, I don't know why I knew that. Thanks רש"י Rashi for
telling me that what you do in a שול shul is you
pray and what you do in a בית מדרש Beis Medrash is
you learn. I'm not sure why רש"י Rashi had to say that.
Anyway, okay, anyway, 394 of each one of, שולs, shul 394 בתי
מדרשות, batei midrashot, 394 major בתי דינים. batei dinim. Okay, וכנגדם בתי
סופרים ve-kenegdam batei sofrim and also an equal amount of scribal homes,
where now here רש"י Rashi is clarifying, רש"י Rashi says ללמד תינוקות,
le-lamed tinokot, which doesn't mean people actually scribed, which you could have
said it meant, but anyway רש"י Rashi says it means people like,
which is
the בית ספר, Beis Sefer,
like חדר, Cheder, right, exactly. דיינים
טובא הוו. Dayanim tuva havu. So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
so you see it's not just, there weren't just two or three,
there were like I mean 300 just
בתי דינים. batei dinim. They weren't גוזרי גזירות, gozrei gezerot, exactly. Anyway,
so
the גמרא Gemara says וכי קאמרינן אגוזרי גזירות קאמרינן, ve-chi ka-amrinan a-gozrei
gezerot ka-amrinan,
we were speaking about those that particularly weren't just judges, but they
particularly,
actually made, made rules, made made, what? Yeah, well they had some
specialty, but again it seems like גוזרי גזירות gozrei gezerot is not
just that they just applied the law, but they actually set down
certain parameters and
certain guidelines and again, somehow they also played a legislative role and
not just a judicial role. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב אסי,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav Assi, גוזרי גזירות שבירושלים, gozrei gezerot she-biYerushalayim, those who would do
this, who's would be these judges that would obviously have some very
special status in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, make the, that would be making these
edicts, היו נוטלין שכרן תשעים ותשעה מנה hayu notlin sacharam tishim ve-tisha
maneh מתרומת הלשכה. mi-trumat ha-lishka. They would get their fee
99 talents of silver, that'd be a lot. So according to him,
I assume there were a lot of these גוזרי גזירות שבירושלים gozrei
gezerot she-biYerushalayim as opposed to what we just said a minute ago,
or else that seems like a little bit overpaying for these two
or three judges. They'd get 99 talents of silver
from the תרומת הלשכה, trumat ha-lishka, from the money that they had
collected when they collected the מחצית השקל. machatzis ha-shekel. So they used
the base money for the קרבנות, korbanot, but the extra moneys they
would use to for ongoing sort of בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash needs
or some general types of communal services the money would go to.
And one of the things it would go to would be paying
the salary of these גוזרי גזירות. gozrei gezerot.
Now they can't be judges, right, because you don't take שכר לדון?
schar la-dun?
Well, so we're going to, yeah, so we're going to talk about
that about the whole problem about about taking money for for fee
for judging. So hold on, we'll get to that. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay,
לא רצו, lo ratzu, if they didn't want to accept that money,
מוסיפין להם, mosifin lahem, you you increase their salary. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא רצו, lo ratzu, they didn't want to judge with
that money... אטו
ברשיעי עסקינן? Atu berishaye askinan? What, we're dealing with like wicked people?
I mean, you know, you're supposed to be a judge, you know,
we're paying you your money. What do you mean? Like, you refuse?
You're negotiating your salary? So it's interesting. Then the גמרא Gemara says
אלא, ella, that's no, it's just like it just seems like it's
just arbitrary, "no, I don't want to". So we have to, what,
we have to bribe you? אלא לא ספקו. ella lo safku. It
means if it wasn't enough, it wasn't enough for their needs. Basically
we're trying to make sure that they're provided for. Okay, אף על
פי שלא רצו, af al pi shelo ratzu, now and then it
switches it. Even if it makes them from רשעים reshayim to צדיקים.
tzadikim. If it wasn't enough for their needs, even if they were
refusing to take more, מוסיפין עליהם, mosifim aleihem, you'd still give them
more, you'd make sure that it would cover their needs. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: קרנא, Karna, now we're
going to have to figure this out, what is this doing that
they're getting paid for their job as judges? Okay, and we'll take
a look at a few stories that seems to be something that
is very suspicious. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says
קרנא, Karna, a judge by the name of קרנא, Karna, הוה שקיל
איסתירא, hava shakil istira, he would accept a סלע, sela, a coin,
right, מזכאי ואיסתירא מחייב. mizakai veistira mechayav. When people would come to
him for a judgment, he would make both sides pay him whatever,
20 bucks or $100, whatever it would be. Right?
קרנא Karna guy?
Yeah, אמורא קרנא. Amora Karna. First generation אמורא. Amora.
Thank you, yeah I thought he was very early.
His name, it means monetary fund.
Exactly. Okay, so when judges would, when people would come to him,
he would make both sides pay the fee so that he would,
it wouldn't be a concern about bribe, it wouldn't be a concern
about favoring one side over the other, they each would pay equal
court costs. Exactly.
Okay, so let's take a look. ודיין להו דינא, vedayan lehu dina,
and then he would judge their case. He does this beforehand?
Yeah, he would pay, after, no, but wait, but no, I
know, you don't know yet who's the זכאי, zakai, who's the חייב.
chayav. It means, it means each side pays and then he would
judge their case. Okay, והיכי עביד הכי? veheichi avid hachi? How could
he do that? והכתיב שוחד לא תקח, vehachtiv shochad lo tikach, don't
take bribes. Now, there's two reasons this isn't bribe. Number one, it's
not only from one side, and number two, it's done for court
costs. As the גמרא Gemara says, bribes are often beforehand. So וכי
תימא הני מילי היכא דשקיל מחד גיסא, vechi teima hani mili heicha
deshakeil mechada gisa, so the גמרא Gemara looks at it, maybe it's
only considered a bribe if you only take from one
side. דילמא אתי לאצלויי דינא, dilma ati leatzloyei dina, maybe you'll come
to incline the judgment according to the side you took it from.
וקרנא כיון דשקיל מתרוייהו לא אתי לאצלויי דינא, veKarna keivan deshakeil mitravaihu
lo ati leatzloyei dina, but Karna because he took from both sides
he won't come to incline in favor of one side? So the
גמרא Gemara says, וכי לא אתי לאצלויי דינא מי שרי? vechi lo
ati leatzloyei dina mi sharei?
But since when is that permissible, even if you are not, it's
not going to lead to you to incline the judgment? והתניא, vehatanya,
תנא ברייתא, tana baraisa, שוחד לא תקח, shochad lo tikach, do not
take a bribe. מה תלמוד לומר? mah talmud lomar? What's it telling
you? אם ללמד שלא לזכות את החייב ושלא לחייב את הזכאי, im
lelamed shelo lezakot et hachayav veshelo lechayev et hazakai, don't take a
bribe with the intention of perverting the judgment, to, you know, find
in favor of the one who's guilty and rule against the one
who's innocent or who is, you know, who should be
exempt. הרי הוא כבר נאמר, harei hu kvar ne'emar, לא תטה משפט,
lo tateh mishpat, don't pervert the judgment. So you don't need to
say don't take a bribe, you're already told you can't pervert the
judgment. Which makes it worse. אלא אפילו לזכות את הזכאי ולחייב את
החייב אמרה תורה שוחד לא תקח. ella afilu lezakot et hazakai ulechayev
et hachayav amrah Torah shochad lo tikach. Even if your intent was
to do the judgment properly, to make the innocent one innocent and
the guilty one guilty, you can't take a bribe. Now we have
to ask ourselves what's going on with the guy who's paying the
bribe? What's he saying? So is he saying like "here's a thousand
dollars, find in favor of me" and you're taking the bribe but
in your head you're saying "I'm really just going to judge it,
you know, honestly"? That's one idea, like, so you know he's trying
to get you to do one thing and you're in your mind
believe you're not going to follow what he's asking. Or another scenario
which is I believe the scenario that the גמרא Gemara is talking
about is that somebody says, "look, you know, here's a thousand dollars,
all I ask from you is to give me a fair judgment.
You know, if I'm innocent find me innocent, you know, and here
take this money. I don't ask you to find me guilty if
I'm innocent or find me innocent if I'm guilty, just judge me
fairly if I'm genuinely innocent." So okay, fine, you know. So that,
even so, you can't take it because obviously even if that's the
arrangement, you know, some things, it could lead to to being inclined
in his favor regardless. אפילו לזכות הזכאי ולחייב החייב אמרה תורה שוחד
לא תקח. afilu lezakot hazakai ulechayev hachayav amrah Torah shochad lo tikach.
So now, so the גמרא Gemara says if that's true, shouldn't it
be better if you take it from both sides? Because taking from
both sides, how is that better than anyway just taking the money
and trying to do and agreeing to just do the right thing,
which is a pretty... right, which is why it's a very funny
question because it's one thing to take it from one side and
agree, "I'm telling you I'm only going to judge as fairly, you
know, fine", but at the end of the day you took money
from one side, that changes your attitude towards that one side. If
you took an equal fee from both, then it's then it's all
equal. So it's funny that the גמרא Gemara thinks that they're in
the same category. You could have easily have argued that once you
take an equal amount from both sides, you know, there's no, it
doesn't get defined that way.
Right. Okay, that could be. So if the איסור issur is doing
it even after the end of the case and even after you've
made up your mind, then it's prohibiting like any money. But even
so, okay, anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers. So the
גמרא Gemara will say, הני
מילי, hani milei, fine. That's a problem, but that's היכא דשקיל בתורת
שוחד. heicha deshakeil betorat shochad. That's when you're taking it as a
bribe, okay? Or as a gift, let's say. האי תנא בתורת אגרא
הוה שקיל. hai tanna betorat agra hava shakeil.
He was taking it just as a courtesy, so therefore at, you
know, as expenses. So רש"י Rashi says בתורת שוחד שלא תחייבני אם
זכאי אני, betorat shochad shelo techayveni im zakai ani, that somehow, again,
it's לחיוב את החייב ולזכות את הזכאי, lechayeyv et hachayav ulezakot et
hazakai, but you're making it still about the final judgment that you're
going to issue. Here's some money, I want you to just judge
me fairly. So any amount that's given that connects itself to the
judgment, even if presumably a fair judgment, is considered שוחד. shochad. Here
it has not related to the end judgment at all. It's just,
you know, you gotta pay me for my time, you gotta pay
me for my services, okay? And therefore it's not called שוחד. shochad.
Presumably though, even that's only okay if it comes equally from both
sides, okay? So according to this, if both sides were to give
you a hundred dollars on the condition that you judge them favorably
or you judge them fairly, you wouldn't be allowed to take the
money. But if each side gives you a hundred dollars just for
your fee, for your expenses and your whatever, you know, your services,
then you would be able to. Yes?
What if one side couldn't afford to pay?
Yeah, that's a good question. Well, that's also, I don't know. So
then, you know, that's a good question. Would they have like a
fund? I don't know how they'd handle that. So the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, what, yeah, public defender. Exactly, exactly. So now
the גמרא Gemara questions this. ובתורת אגרא מי שרי? uvetorat agra mi
sharei? One minute. Even just as a fee for services? So it's
from both sides, it's balanced, and it's about services, it's not about
the judgment. So nevertheless, since when is that allowed? דתנן, detnan, we
taught in a משנה: Mishnah: הנוטל שכר לדון דיניו בטילים. hanoteil sachar
ladun dinav beteilim. Anybody who gets a fee for his judgment, his
judgment is void. And you know, again, is that because there's a
concern of שוחד? shochad? Is it just because basically you're supposed to
be judging as representing God, not as a servant, not as being
paid by the people? But it voids the judgment. So the גמרא
Gemara says הני מילי אגר דינא. hani milei agar dina.
That's if you're actually paid for the judgment. No, but also means,
it also means the fee for the
services for rendering judgment. הכא אגר בטלה הוה שקיל. hacha agar batala
hava shakeil. As opposed to being paid for the work that you
are giving up by not being, the fact that I have to
leave my job in order to come here and sit and judge
you, so you're not actually paying me to do the judgment, what
you're paying me to do is to take time off from my
job. Okay, so that's called שכר בטלה. sachar batala. Well, we'll get
to that in a minute. That's תוספות Tosafot gets back to the
question about why these דיינים dayanim got paid
from the תרומת הלשכה. terumat halishka. So this becomes an important discussion
within הלכה, halacha, which is you're not supposed to get paid for
doing a מצוה. mitzvah. Which basically means that תורה Torah teachers and
doctors among others and judges or whatever are not supposed to be
paid. So basically rabbis and so on. Yeah, but besides the שבת
Shabbos point, you're not supposed to, you know, it says the גמרא
Gemara quotes a פסוק, pasuk, I think it's ראה למדתי אתכם re'eh
limadeti etchem or is it מה אני בחינם אף אתם בחינם? mah
ani bechinam af atem bechinam? I don't think that was the פסוק,
pasuk, but anyway it says מה אני בחינם אף אתם בחינם. mah
ani bechinam af atem bechinam. The same way I got taught, you
Moses, without asking any fees, you have to teach the people for
free. So the question is, you know, and רמב"ם Rambam of course
goes through a whole thing about that, about not only not teaching
for a fee, but also particularly not learning in כולל, kollel, and
he points out about how all the rabbis had professions and so
on. Okay, but obviously it's very hard, you know, and we're at
different times when being a rabbi and so on was a specialized
class or not. But people do have to put food on the
table. So, didn't רמב"ם Rambam have a brother supporting him?
Well, yeah, so that's why it's also easier to say those things.
So anyway, so what happens is it develops this principle called שכר
בטלה. sachar batala. שכר בטלה sachar batala is we're not paying you
actually for teaching תורה Torah or for being a doctor, we're paying
you for the fact that you're not going ahead and doing something
else during this same time and you're taking off from your other
job. So the question is, is that actually called opportunity cost? If
that were true, the people that should get a higher salary are
not the better doctors and the better rabbis, but the people that
actually have a higher market value in some other area. So if
you have some guy that left being a lawyer to be a
rabbi, even if he's a terrible rabbi but he's making a lot
of money as a lawyer, you should have to pay him more
than somebody who is an amazing rabbi but not good at doing
anything else. So anyway, it becomes a little bit of funny, and
then we figure well שכר בטלה sachar batala is not just the
job that you could be getting now, it's also all of the
jobs you could have gotten had you not gotten. gone to like
rabbinical school and had you not been, anyway. What? Is there an
end run around this? I,
yeah, I mean, that's the end run, but it becomes a little
bit of a fiction. Anyway, so that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says is you cannot get paid
for actually rendering judgment, for some reason he even voids the judgments,
which is interesting. But what you can do is you can get
paid for the שכר בטלה s'char batala. *schar batala*.
Why Jewish education is free.
There you go, exactly. Okay. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, one minute. רמינהי ואגב בטלה מי
שרי *Raminihi ve'agav batala mi sharei*? Okay. How's that go? ואגב בטלה
מי שרי *Ve'agav batala mi sharei*? Was it, is it really allowed
to get שכר בטלה s'char batala *schar batala*? Like a, what's that
called, opportunity cost? Okay. והתניא וקתני בברייתא *Vehatanya vekatani bevaraita*: מכוער הדיין
שנוטל שכר לדון, אלא שדינו דין *Mechoar hadayan shenotel schar ladun, ella
shedino din*. Disgusting is the judge who takes fees for his judgment,
but it still is a binding judgment. היכי דמי *Heichi dami*? What's
the case? אילימא אגר דינא *Ilima agar dina*, if it's actual fee
for rendering judgment, דינו דין *dino din*? How is it binding? והתניא
*Vehatanya*, we just taught earlier: הנוטל שכר לדון דיניו בטלים *Hanotel schar
ladun dinav betelim*, that the judgments are void if you get paid.
אלא אגר בטלה *Ella agar batala*, it must be
for opportunity cost that you're getting paid for the job you're not
doing. וקתני מכוער הדיין *Vekatani mechoar hadayan*, and we still say that
it's disgusting. So we're still back to the problem of how קרנא
*Karna* took the money. You're not supposed to even take אגר בטלה
*agar batala*, שכר בטלה s'char batala *schar batala*. So the גמרא gemara,
*Gemara* says: No. הני מילי בטלה דלא מוכח *Hani milei batala dela
muchach*. That's when it's not obvious that you are losing any money
by sitting in, by rendering judgment and by spending your time with
these guys. Then it, then from people's perspective, it looks wrong. It
looks like you're being paid to render judgment, even though in fact
you're just being paid to leave your other job. So if it's
not obvious, then it's מכוער הדבר *mechoar hadavar*. But קרנא בטלה דמוכח
הוי שקיל *Karna batala demuchach havei shakil*. קרנא *Karna*, it was very
obvious that he was being paid because he had to leave his
other job. So when you're only being paid for the job you're
not doing and it's obvious, and therefore nobody suspects you of being
paid for the judgment you are rendering, then it's acceptable. How was
it obvious by קרנא *Karna*? דהוה טוהי באמבארא דחמרא *Dehavei tohei be'ambara
dechamra*. He would basically be a wine smeller. He would smell in
like the... Sommelier? Right, yeah. And he would be able to smell
the wine and determine whether it was about to spoil and tell
people which one they should sell sooner rather than the other one.
ויהבי ליה זוזא *Veyahavi lei zuza*, and they would give him a,
like a dollar, meaning so it would be very obvious that here's
somebody that like, you know, again, I don't know how it was
obvious that he wasn't doing his job, but somehow it was very
obvious that he could earn some easy money. All he would have
to do would be walk into a guy's, you know, wine store
or whatever, or storehouse and do some smelling and they'd give him
money. So it's very obvious to anybody that from me spending time
sitting with you, I'm losing money elsewhere and therefore people will understand
that that's what the money is about.
Okay. כי הא דרב הונא *Ki ha deRav Huna*, like this story
of רב הונא *Rav Huna*. כי הוה אתי דינא לקמיה *Ki havei
atei dina lekaimei*, when a judgment would come in front of him,
אמר amar להו *amar lehu*, he said to the litigants: הבו לי
גברא דדלי לי בחריתאי *Havu li gavra dedali li becharitai*. You know
what? I'm happy to sit in to hear your case, as long
as you provide me some man that will go ahead and will
draw water in my place. I get paid for drawing water, so
find somebody to go ahead and do that job for me so
I will still get my normal, you know, fee for the normal
work I would do
today, ואידון לכו דינא *ve'idun lechu dina*, and then I'll judge your
case. Okay. So now we're going to get onto a discussion about
שוחד shochad, *shochad*, but what we basically have come up with is
you're not supposed to be paid. Now, is it you're not supposed
to be paid? I broadened the discussion because this is also where
you get the issue of שכר בטלה *schar batala* to other types
of מצוות *mitzvot*, like learning תורה *Torah* and so on, and being
a doctor, etc. And that could be part of what it is.
But one also wonders that if it says that you actually do
get paid, it's דיניו בטלים *dinav betelim*, right? It sounds like it's
more than just the problem of not supposed to get paid for
a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*. It's that if you're directly being paid for
rendering judgment, it draws it much closer to the idea of שוחד
shochad *shochad* and therefore we're voiding the judgment. So the only, so
there's two issues here. There's real שוחד shochad. *shochad*, which is money
that is paid with a focus on what the end judgment will
be. And even if it's to do the right end judgment, but
money that's paid for the sake of the end judgment is שוחד
shochad. *shochad*. Money that's paid for actually the service is not שוחד
shochad *shochad*, but it seems that because it's close to שוחד shochad
*shochad* or whatever, therefore it's void. And the only thing that's acceptable,
even if you give it, the judgments are void. The only thing
that's acceptable is to be paying for the money, for the work
that you're not doing. Now if you take a look at תוספות
tosfot *Tosafot*, גזרי גזרות שבירושלים *Gozei gezeirot shebiYerushalayim*, let's go back to
those that were paid from the, from the
public funds. Okay, because now we've done this whole discussion about how
he got paid from the actual litigants. Is it any different when
you're paid from the public funds? When we say these גזרי גזרות
*gozei gezeirot* were paid, would that be also their שכר בטלה *schar
batala*? What was that money about? Okay. So let's look at this
תוספות tosfot *Tosafot*: גזרי גזרות שבירושלים היו נוטלין שכר מתרומת הלשכה *Gozei
gezeirot shebiYerushalayim hayu notlin schar mitrumat halishka*. He says... So why is
this different and do you need to give essentially also the same
answer? Do you have to say that these public funds ultimately were
like a type of a שכר בטלה? So אמר רבינו תם Amar
Rabbeinu Tam משום דלא אסור אלא מבעלי דינין. mishum de-lo assur ela
mi-ba'alei dinin. No,
the only problem since it's about being in the ambit of שוחד,
shochad the only problem is if you're taking money from the litigants.
So even if you're taking them from both litigants and even if
blah blah blah all those issues and you're being paid for your
services, that's only a problem when it's coming from the litigants, okay,
because then it's possibly within the ambit of שוחד shochad even if
it's not exactly שוחד. shochad, אבל הכא משל ציבור, Aval hacha mi-shol
tzibur, here you
are being paid from communal funds so it was absolutely not a
problem to be paid for your services. We don't have to make
it שכר בטלה. We only have to right even though it's being
paid for services nevertheless as long as it's not coming from the
litigants you're fine. That's answer number one. ורבי מפרש דהכא לאו בתורת
שכר היו נוטלים אלא הכא כל שעה היו יושבין בדין ולא היו
עוסקין בשום מלאכה ולא היה להם במה להתפרנס והיה מוטל על הציבור
לפרנסם. Ve-Rebbi mefareish de-hacha lav betorat s'char hayu notlim ela hacha kol
sha'a hayu yoshvin badin velo hayu oskin beshum melacha velo haya lahem
bema le-hitparnes vehaya mutal al hatzibur lefarnesam.
So he gives a different answer. He says no no no look.
He says you need some people right to actually be dedicated to
being available to do this job. So you a it means there
won't be any good you can't give them שכר בטלה because they
don't have another job that they're leaving but the community needs them
dedicated to this job. Now what you could have said is once
you're needed to be dedicated to this job then we have to
basically we're allowed to pay you directly. But תוספות tosfot doesn't make
that cause you still got a problem how could you be paying
them directly you're not supposed to pay somebody for these types of
services. No
but since we need you dedicated to this job and we're telling
you not to get another job then now you become basically paupers
because you don't have any means of support. So we have forced
you to have no other means of support and now we have
a responsibility to provide for you because of your you know because
you're because basically you don't have any money not because we're paying
you directly for your services. So it's interesting different models right. The
reason I put it out there is because like we basically think
like oh no we can't do the שכר בטלה model we want
somebody to be a good rabbi or be a good school teacher
or be a good doctor then they have to basically focus all
their energies on that right. But then the next step that we
take is and therefore we're going to pay them directly for those
services. תוספות tosfot is still trying to like work around this problem.
You're still not supposed to pay somebody for doing a מצוה. mitzvah
So if we're going to tell you to devote yourself to this
we're going to pay you not for the מצוה you're doing we're
going to pay you because now we have to support you. Now
we have a communal responsibility to support you. Okay. Was רבי Rebbi
רבינו יהודה הנשיא? Rabbeinu Yehuda HaNasi? No there's one פשט p'shat is
רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam and the other is רבי. Rebbi. No no
no no no. No this תוספות tosfot was written by a תלמידי
talmidei of
רבינו שמשון Rabbeinu Shimshon the ר"ש. Rash. So when he says רבי
Rebbi it was written by a it was
written by a student of the ר"ש Rash so it refers to
רבינו שמשון. Rabbeinu Shimshon. Oh so so when it says רבי Rebbi
here in this תוספות tosfot he means רבינו שמשון. Rabbeinu Shimshon. You
mean you mean the ר"ש? Rash? This particular תוספות tosfot was written
by
a תלמיד talmid of the ר"ש. Rash.
When you read like תלמידי רבינו פרץ
talmidei
Rabbeinu Peretz
and they say רבינו Rabbeinu or רבי Rebbi it means רבינו פרץ.
Rabbeinu Peretz. Right. Okay. I'm not chal... Like how do you... How
do I know that this was written by רבינו שמשון?
Rabbeinu Shimshon? Because many פרקים perakim back it says from it says
from this point on are the תוספות tosfot of רבינו שמשון. Rabbeinu
Shimshon. Yeah it said that somewhere. I forget. You're calling me out
on us where is it? Oh on דף צ'. daf tzadi.
The beginning the beginning of the tenth פרק perek
it says מכאן עד סוף העתקה מתוספות רבינו שמשון.
mikan ad
sof ha'ataka mi-tosfot Rabbeinu Shimshon.
And where is that? The first תוספות tosfot on דף צ' daf
tzadi on the tenth פרק perek on דף צ' עמוד א'. daf
tzadi amud aleph. I'm overwhelmed if I missed a single תוספות tosfot.
I'm I'm out of it.
And if I didn't know that then I would
look up אורבך בעלי
התוספות
Orbach
Ba'alei
HaTosafot that tells you who the author of the
תוספות tosfot of the different מסכתות masechtot are. But that's so striking
says רבי Rebbi you'd want to know who who is it.
Right it's an early תוספות. tosfot The later תוספות Tosafot lose
that רבי Rebbi thing and they're more speak in a very anonymous
voice but the earlier תוספות which very much come from a particular
you know one of the בעלי התוספות Ba'alei HaTosafot or his school
so you have that language of רבי Rebbi a lot more. Yes
I'm sorry Joe. but if they were, we want them dedicated,
we're not paying them for doing a מצווה, mitzvah, we're doing, now
they're dedicated, and now their responsibility of support is on us, the
community. Okay, now the גמרא gemara goes back and says like this.
אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abahu,
now we get into a little discussion about שוחד. shochad Says רבי
אבהו, Rabbi Abahu, בוא וראה כמה סמיות עיניהם של מקבלי שוחד.
bo u're kama smuyot
eineihem shemekablei shochad. Come see how blind are the eyes of those
who accept bribes. אדם חש בעיניו, adam chash be'einav, a person has
a problem in his eye, נותן ממון לרופא, noten mamon l'rofe, he
gives some money to a doctor, ספק נתרפא ספק אינו מתרפא, safek
nitrapeh safek eino mitrapeh, it's questionable whether the doctor will heal the
eye or not. So he gives money and you don't know whether
it's going to do any good to heal the eye. והן נוטלין
שוה פרוטה, v'hen notlin shaveh prutah, and these people who accept bribes,
they take just a dollar, וסמיות עיניהם, u'smuyot eineihen, and it has
the power to blind their eyes, a little bit of money blinds
their eyes, שנאמר כי השוחד יעור פקחים, shene'emar ki hashochad ya'aver pikchim,
because the bribery will blind the open-eyed. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our
Rabbis taught, כי השוחד יעור עיני חכמים, ki hashochad ya'aver einei chachamim,
the שוחד shochad will blind the eyes of sages, קל וחומר לטיפשין,
kal v'chomer l'tipshim, how much more so will it blind the you
know the stupid. ויסלף דברי צדיקים, v'isaleif divrei tzadikim, and pervert the
words of the righteous, קל וחומר לרשעים, kal v'chomer l'rasha'im, how much
more so will it pervert the words of the wicked. Meaning so
here you have people that actually are, you know, the normal people
who you assume take bribe are the, you know, are the wicked
people. But here even the righteous people and they're trying to do
the right thing, and like I said, maybe they're just taking it
and they're planning on judging correctly, nevertheless, look how it will pervert
and blind them, how much more so will it do people who
are intentionally trying to do the wrong thing. אטו טיפשין ורשעים בני
דינא נינהו, atu tipshim u'rasha'im bnei dina ninhu, the גמרא Gemara doesn't,
can't imagine that these people would have been appointed judges to the
in the first place. How did we get stupid and wicked people
as judges? Why do you have to say קל וחומר? kal v'chomer?
Of course our judges are all righteous and and wise. אלא הכי
קאמר, ela hachi ka'amar, this is what it means. כי השוחד יעור
עיני חכמים, ki hashochad ya'aver einei chachamim, אפילו חכם גדול, afilu chacham
gadol, even somebody who is a great sage, ולוקח שוחד, v'loke'ach shochad,
and takes a bribe, אינו נפטר מן העולם בלא סמיות הלב, eino
niftar min ha'olam b'lo smiyut halev, he does not leave the world
without his heart being blinded, which basically the way תוספות says it
means that first times he takes שוחד shochad. he's a חכמים. chachamim.
The second time he takes שוחד shochad. he's a טיפשין tipshin because
by that time the שוחד shochad. has already made him stupid. ויסלף
דברי צדיקים, v'isaleif divrei tzadikim, אפילו צדיק גמור ולוקח שוחד, afilu tzadik
gamur v'loke'ach shochad, even a total צדיק tzadik and he takes שוחד,
shochad. אינו נפטר מן העולם בלא טירוף הדעת, eino niftar min ha'olam
b'lo tiruf hada'at, he doesn't leave the world without sort of going
out of his mind or without, you know, perverting his character and
becoming a רשע, rasha, so he's, so if it perverts him the
first time or demented, if it perverts him the first time how
much more will it pervert him the second and the third. Well
obviously because you know they usually want to have a certain level
of intellectual superiority to be a judge and you know but here
here he's becoming you know stupider, right. כי אתא רב דימי אמר,
ki ata Rav Dimi amar, אמר דרש רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar
darash Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's meant by
the verse, מלך במשפט יעמיד ארץ, melech b'mishpat ya'amid aretz, the king
with justice will like you know stand erect, establish the foundation of
the earth, thank you, establish the foundation of the earth, ואיש תרומות
יהרסנה, v'ish trumot yeherseina, and a man of תרומות trumot which might
mean like from the word מרמה, mirmah, deceit, but we'll see the
גמרא Gemara. will interpret it as the word תרומה trumah will destroy
it. Who is this man of תרומות trumot that will destroy the
world? אם דומה דיין למלך, im domeh dayan l'melech, if the judge
appears like a king, שאינו צריך לכלום, she'eino tzarich l'klum, he doesn't,
he doesn't need anybody, he's never you know doesn't need any favors,
never never asks anything of anyone, self-sufficient, יעמיד ארץ, ya'amid aretz, then
he'll establish the land, then he's not, nobody can take advantage of
him, he's in nobody's pocket. אבל אם דומה לכהן שמחזר על הגרנות,
aval im domeh l'kohen she'mechazer al hagranot, but if he's like the
כהן kohen that has to go from one threshing floor to the
next to get his תרומה, trumah, he's needy, his hand is out,
he he needs other people's favors, יהרסנה, yeherseina, that type of a
judge will destroy the earth. אמר רבה בר רב שילא, amar Rabba
bar Rav Shila, האי דיינא דשאיל שאילתא, hai dayana d'shail she'ilta, if
a judge borrows an object, פסול למידן דינא, pasul l'meidan dina, he's
invalid to give a judgment. So what does it mean he asks
a question? So I did not ask a question I misinterpreted that.
He borrows an object. שאיל שאילתא, shail she'ilta, he borrows an object.
If he he goes to you and he says could I borrow
your ladder, could I borrow two eggs, could I borrow your car
from anybody, from anybody, from anybody, because then within the community he
is somebody that is dependent on other people, it seems like and
he does not come across as a type of a self-sufficient person.
Okay. רש"י Rashi says דרגיל לשאול מבני עירו בבהמות וכלים, d'ragil l'shail
mivnei iro b'hemot v'kelim, a judge, רגיל, ragil, fine, so it's not
just once, but somebody that generally he's like the כהן המחזר על
הגרנות, kohen ha'mechazer al hagranot, right? So he's the guy that always
you know needs stuff, he's somebody that needs favors, so somebody who
needs even if they're like small mundane favors, he's not self-sufficient enough
to be a good judge. Okay, people will give him, meaning once
he did them a favor, but they have to have their day
in court, or whatever people's intention is and then he also will
be partial because of what he's gotten in the past or what
he might anticipate in the future. ולא אמרן אלא דלית ליה לאושולי,
v'lo aman ela d'leis lei l'oshulei, and that's only if he doesn't
have things to lend other people, אבל אית ליה לאושולי, aval is
lei l'oshulei, but if he has what to lend others, there's a
reciprocity. You borrow two eggs from your neighbor one day and you
lend them a cup of sugar the next day. In that case,
לית לן בה, leis lan bah, it's not a problem because then
it's not an issue of a certain power dynamic, right? It's just
being neighborly and, you know, you reciprocate, right? Okay. איני, Eini, is
that really true? רבה ששילתא מדבי בר מריון. Rava shashilta midbei Bar
Maryon. Rava borrowed objects from the house of Bar Maryon, אף גב
דלא שאילי מיניה, af gav d'lo shailei minei, even though he didn't
lend them anything, and presumably, and he, and even though he borrowed
objects from them, he was still willing to judge them. So Gemara
says, התם לאחשובינהו הוא דבעי. hasam lachshuvinhu hu d'baei. No, there he
wasn't doing it because he really needed it, there he was doing
it in order to give them a sense of respect. Oh look,
this great Rabbi came and he borrowed something from us, it makes
them, you know, it flatters them. But still, wouldn't the perception be
negative though? Like, you know... I don't know, you would think that
the perception would be negative and you're right. Yeah, yeah, I don't
know. Oh, of course he ruled now for them, look what he's
borrowed from them.
Yeah, I mean that's I agree, and not only what other people
would
think, you don't want anybody to think, even the people themselves, oh
we've got Rava in our back pocket, he borrowed something from us.
So even if Rava didn't do it because Rava himself needed them,
right, yeah I know it is strange. Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
מאי טעמא דשוחדא? mai tama d'shochda? What is the reason of שוחדא?
shochda? Well, we'll see what it means. But, meaning, but I mean
you know what's the power of שוחדא, shochda, you might want to
say. כיון דקבליה שוחדא מיניה, keivan d'kablah shochda minei, once somebody accepts
a gift from somebody, איקרבא ליה דעתיה לגביה, ikrav leh daatei legabei,
so then meaning, this is like even if you plan on being
fair, right, you're doing it and you're just and all you're doing
is taking the money in order to be fair, you know, but
no, as soon as you take money from somebody, so you feel
close to him, you know, you identify with the person, והוי כגופיה,
v'havei k'gufei, and he becomes like you yourself, ואין אדם רואה חוב
לעצמו, v'ein adam roeh chov l'atzmo, and you're not able to see
your own faults. So meaning, even if you try
to be as completely objective as possible, you can never be fully
objective when it comes to yourself, and when it comes to somebody
else who now you're subconsciously partial to and feel connected to, even
your best attempts you will not be able to be fully objective.
מאי שוחד? mai shochad? And then what does שוחד mean according to
this? שהוא כחד, shehu k'chad,
that you become like one with the person you received the money
from. אמר פפא, Amar Pappa, לא לידון איניש דינא למאן דרחים ליה,
lo lidun inish dina l'man d'rachim leh, a person should not judge
a case to a person that he said he likes or that
he loves, ולא למאן דסני ליה, v'lo l'man d'sani leh, and not
somebody he hates. דרחים ליה לא חזי ליה חובה, d'rachim leh lo
chazi leh chova, somebody he likes he won't be able to see
any you know thing negative about him, right? דסני ליה לא חזי
ליה זכותא, d'sani leh lo chazi leh zachusa, he won't be able
to see any merit. Now, obviously there's a general category which is
talked about, אוהב ושונא, ohev v'soneh, which is somebody who's really well
established as somebody that you really are partial to or you really
don't like. This is talking even about a little bit of a
positive or negative inclination, as we're going to see in a minute
in the Gemara. Okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, האי צורבא מרבנן, hai
tzurva meirabanan, this Torah sage, דמרחמין ליה בני מתא, d'merachmin leh bnei
masa, that the people of the city like him, care for him,
לאו משום דמעלי טפי, lav mishum d'maali tvei, it's not because he's
so great. Oh, if you have a Rabbi that everybody in the
city loves, don't think that shows you that he's a great Rabbi.
אלא משום דלא מוכח להו במילי דשמיא, ella mishum d'lo mochech lhu
b'milei d'shmaya, actually what it shows is that he's not doing his
job, okay, that he's not actually remonstrating them and telling and setting
them straight. So they love him because he panders to them. Okay.
So if you like it, does that mean? There you go. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, well that's a community Rabbi, that's not a teacher.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מריש הוה אמינא, meireish havah amina, I used
to say, הני בני מחוזא, hani bnei Mechuza, the people of מחוזא,
Mechuza, we know that Rava had a whole problem with the people
of מחוזא Mechuza who were cosmopolitan and he didn't always get along
with them so much, these people of מחוזא, Mechuza, כולהו רחמו לי,
kulhu rachmu li, I thought that they all loved me. כיון דהוינא
דיינא, keivan d'havena dayana, once I became a judge and I actually
had a rule against them, some of them at least, אמינא, amina,
then I said, מנייהו סנו לי ומנייהו רחמו לי, minaihu sanu li
u'minaihu rachmu li, some of them hate me, some of them love
me. I figured that the ones that I ruled against hated me
and the ones that I ruled for loved me. Like he very
much assumed that people are just responding not to his own integrity
and who he was as a Rabbi or whatever but like how
much was he nice to them or not nice to them. So
as soon as I'm not nice to them, he figured they didn't
like him anymore. Okay. כיון דחזאי, keivan d'chazai, since I saw, דמאן
דמיחייב ליה האידנא מזכי ליה למחר, d'man d'mechayev leh hai idna mazchei
leh l'machar, that the one that I ruled against today I ruled
in favor of tomorrow. דחזאי d'chazai means he saw or they saw?
Maybe it's they saw. I don't know the grammar. What has the
translation? I saw they saw. I saw. Yeah, that's what I saw.
Since I saw, yeah, anyway, then אמינא, amina, I said you know
what, in the end I'm going to rule in favor of them
and some of them and against them and it's going to change
from day to day and I figured look, אם רחמו כולהו רחמו
לי ואם סנו כולהו סנו לי, im rachmu kulhu rachmu li v'im
sanu kulhu sanu li, look. You know, so which is really like
it's look, stop trying to get everybody to love you, all right.
You've got right you can't satisfy everyone's got. You know, he assumed,
it's a fascinating I love to learn because it really is true,
like you figure like, oh, I gotta do this in order that
they'll like me, I gotta find favor, you know, I gotta rule
nicely for them. As soon
as I say something against them, they're not going to love me.
And you cannot be a good rabbi or a good judge if
you're always worried about what people think about you. So eventually he
realized it's not going to matter anyway because I'm going to have
to rule sometimes in favor and sometimes against people. So look, whatever
they feel about me, they feel about me. I can't let that
bother me, okay, which is a very powerful גמרא, I think. Okay,
same with educators suggest to kids ever that they teach for love
rather than they love teaching. There you go, okay. All right. There's
that great there's the great New Yorker cartoon, I forget exactly what
the line is, but these two businessmen in a bar and one
of them says something like, you know, when I started out, I
wanted to be like you know you know I wanted to be
like loved and admired. He says, I settled for like you know
feared and fear and fear and respect, it was something like that.
Yeah, okay. All right, anyway, okay. תנו רבנן: tanu rabanan: ושחד לא
תקח. veshochad lo tikach. אינו צריך לומר שוחד ממון, eino tzarich lomar
shochad mamon, it goes without saying that you can't actually take money
bribes, אלא אפילו שוחד דברים, ela afilu shochad devarim, even like, you
know, bribes of words נמי אסור, nami assur, מדלא כתיב בצע, midelo
ketiv betza, it doesn't say בצע, betza, which is some the word
of like gain, which is money, לא תקח. lo tikach. היכי דמי
שוחד דברים? heichi dami shochad devarim? What would be a case of
a like שוחד דברים? shochad devarim? It could be like flattery, other
types of words. כי הא דשמואל הוה עבר במעברא. ki ha deshmuel
hava avar bemaavra. Shmuel was passing through a you know on a
on a bridge. אתא הוא גברא יהב ליה ידא, ata hu gavra
yehav lei yada, a certain man came, gave him his hand to
help him across the bridge. אמר ליה מאי עבידתך? amar lei mai
avidetach? So Shmuel said to him, like, what are you doing? What,
you know, what brings you here? אמר ליה, amar lei, or why
or maybe it sounds more like why are you why did you
stretch out your hand to help me? We'll see. אמר ליה דינא
אית לי, amar lei dina it lee, because I have a court
case coming in front of you. So I figured I'd come how
I you know that's why why that's why I'm here or that's
why I stuck up my hand to help you. אמר ליה פסילנא
לך לדינא. amar lei psilna lach ledina. You've invalidated me for you
to be a judge. אמימר הוה יתיב וקא דיין דינא. ameimar hava
yativ veka dayan dina. I'm going to read a few of the
cases and then I'm going to step back and say something about
it. He was judging case, וקא דיין דינא. veka dayan dina. פרח
גדפא ארישיה, parach gadpa areishei, a feather fell on his head. אתא
הוא גברא שקליה, ata hu gavra shaklei, a certain person came and
took the feather off his head. אמר ליה מאי עבידתך? amar lei
mai avidetach? What, you know, what what are you doing? אמר ליה
דינא אית לי, amar lei dina it lee, because I have a
judgment here with you. אמר ליה פסילנא לך לדינא, amar lei psilna
lach ledina, okay, so now you've invalidated me to be a judge
for you. מר עוקבא הוה שדי רוקא קמיה. mar ukva hava shadi
roka kumei. Mar Ukva spat in front of him. אתא הוא גברא
כסייה, ata hu gavra kasyei, a certain person came and covered up
the spit. אמר ליה מאי עבידתך? amar lei mai avidetach? What are
you doing? אמר ליה דינא אית לי, amar lei dina it lee,
I have a judgment here with you. אמר ליה פסילנא לך לדינא.
amar lei psilna lach ledina. You've invalidated me as a judge. Now,
before we get onto it. So it's interesting that the גמרא gives
us this example as אפילו שוחד דברים, afilu shochad devarim, right? Because
is this about words or does שוחד דברים shochad devarim mean like
things, not words, but like actions? Actions. שוחד by actions. And the
part of the question I also wonder here is that is it
specifically only a problem because in the context of doing this, he
said, I have a judgment with you? Right? If the guy had
come and he was bumped into him in the street and he
saw and he opened the door for him because this was Shmuel
or he covered up the spit or he got some feather off
of him and then three hours later he showed up in his
court, would he say, oh no, I can't be a judge because
you did me a favor three hours ago? Right? Maybe, but maybe
not. Maybe it was only because the favor came in the context
of saying who I oh well I have a judgment, so then
it framed that favor in the context of the judgment you know
that's going to be coming and that made it particularly an issue
of שוחד. And I wonder if that's also like the שוחד דברים.
shochad devarim. Again, I don't know. I'm curious how they translate the
word דברים devarim there in your English translation. They translate as words
or as words? Words. Words. So I wonder if it's specifically because
he uses the words to frame, oh, I'm here and I'm doing
this and whatever, you know, I have a judgment, and that's in
the context of this favor, that those words that essentially make it
a type of a שוחד. Yes. But he actually means something different
than we're interpreting it. For example, yeah. It's a little stupid and
inane to say I helped you over the bridge because I'm here
to have a judgment.
It's so transparent. Right. What if he says this but he meant
it's only because I have to be here that I was able
to help you. No no no, so you're right, that is what
I think he did say. Meaning, I'm sorry if I wasn't clear,
I do think he said like, oh,
I'm passing by because I have a judgment. But nevertheless, he brought
the issue of the judgment into the conversation.
Right, but you're right, it's not like I'm doing you this favor
because, right? That would be a little bit too transparent. Right. But
I still think that the דברים devarim here could be if he
had just done a favor and an hour later he showed up
in. in the court, right, but because he connected it, he said,
oh, I'm here because I was passing by, I have a judgment,
kind of connects it. Jonathan, you wanted to say something? The note
says something? My Artscroll note says by דברים Devarim says a service
or other non-monetary favor done for the judge.
So it's reading דברים Devarim as the service, not as the words.
Action, an
action, not as the words. I think it's a little vague because
I think it is interesting that the גמרא goes out of its
way to say in each of these cases he explicitly mentioned the
upcoming judgment in the context of the favor, yes. It says it's
possibly in the same way, but the same way as Jonathan just
said? Yes. But it's interesting that like why, you know, somebody does
you this minor favor and they say, why did you do that
for? It's like it was something unusual that the person did something
extraordinary that you wouldn't expect an ordinary passerby to do, right. So
that could be that too. Okay, so let's take a look now
at the next case in the גמרא. Okay. רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי
Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Yossi הוי רגיל havay ragil אריסיה, arisei, רבי ישמעאל
ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Yossi his sharecropper generally, דהוה מייתי ליה
dehavay mayti lei כנתא דפירי kanta depeiri כל מעלי שבתא kol ma'alei
Shabta every Friday would bring him כנתא דפירי kanta depeiri like a
basket of fruit from, you know, his own fields. This was his,
you know, his percentage from the field. יומא חד yoma chad אייתי
ליה ayti lei בהמשא בשבתא, bahamsha beShabta, one day he brought him
on Thursday. אמר ליה amar lei מאי שנא האידנא, mai shna ha'idna,
why are you bringing it early this week? אמר ליה amar lei
דינא אית לי dina it li because I had to come early
into town because I've got a judgment, a court case, ואמינא ve'amina
אגב אורחאי agav orchai אייתי ליה למר. ayti lei lemar. Since on
my way to court or whatever, presumably, and you're going to, he's
going to be the judge, which wasn't said explicitly, but I had
to come into the city anyway, I figured I'd bring you my,
the food a day early. So לא קביל מיניה. lo kabil minei.
So he refused to accept it from him because אמר ליה amar
lei פסילנא לך לדינא, psilna lach ledina, you've invalidated me to be
a judge for you now, because having gotten that favor, even though
it was his food, but getting it a day early, that would
have inclined me, you know, that would have been a type of
a שוחד. The sharecropper was the judge? No. The sharecropper was bringing
it to רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Yossi who was
the judge. Right. So he was giving רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי's Rabbi
Yishmael beRabbi Yossi portion of the produce, he gave it to him
a day early and he says, now I can't be your judge.
Okay, again, but notice in this case, he also specifically made mention
of the fact that he was coming in for the judgment. אותיב
oteiv זוגא דרבנן, zuga derabbanan, so he sat a pair of rabbis,
ודיינין ליה, vedaynin lei, and they were judging him, not him. Okay,
now of course people ask what do you mean two? Shouldn't he
mean three rabbis? And you know I'll get back to that in
a minute. ובהדי דקאזיל ואתי, uvahadi deka'azil ve'ati, so there he was,
this guy his sharecropper was sitting with these other two rabbis who
were judging him and רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Yossi
was just wandering around, he was overhearing, he was listening, he was
walking back and forth. ובהדי דקאזיל ואתי, uvahadi deka'azil ve'ati, אמר amar
אי בעי טעין הכי ei ba'ei ta'in hachi ואי בעי טעין הכי,
ve'ei ba'ei ta'in hachi, you know he should make this claim, he
should make that claim, like he was all of a sudden he
found himself thinking about how he could argue in favor of this
guy. אמר Amar. he said, תיפח נפשם tipach nafsham של מקבלי שוחד,
shel mekablei shochad, blasted be the souls of those who accept bribes.
ומה אני umah ani שלא נטלתי, shelo natalti, number one I even
refused to take it, and number two, ואם נטלתי ve'im natalti שלי
נטלתי, sheli natalti, had I taken it, it was my food anyway,
I just would have gotten it a day early, and nevertheless I
find myself thinking about how I could come and argue for this
guy's side just because of that little favor he would have done
for me that I didn't even accept. המקבלי שוחד hamekablei shochad על
אחת כמה וכמה, al achat kama vechama, so somebody who actually takes,
המקבלי שוחד hamekablei shochad so, so that's how I respond, המקבלי שוחד
hamekablei shochad על אחת כמה וכמה, al achat kama vechama, imagine how
people actually accept bribes even if they're thinking about doing it and
judging fairly, look how much it biases you at a subconscious level.
Okay, now by the way, the fact that it was only two
rabbis he had sit there, the מהרש"א Maharsha asks why two, why
not three? So the מהרש"א Maharsha suggests he says maybe the only
problem is is that if you are the sole judge, but maybe
not that you could literally take a bribe, but by things like
this, little favors or things like that, he says maybe it wouldn't
be such a problem if you were one of three, you were
a panel of three, you got a little favor, okay, whatever. But
he says it doesn't sound like that, it doesn't sound like רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael remained on the בית דין, Beis Din, it sounds
like he was walking around and he had the other people actually
be on the court. He was the third now. What? Maybe that
was it. Yeah. All right, case, רבי ישמעאל ברבי אלישע Rabbi Yishmael
beRabbi Elisha אייתי ליה, ayti lei, so one other story like this,
רבי ישמעאל ברבי אלישע, Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Elisha, so they brought him
ההוא גברא hahu gavra ראשית הגז. reishis hagez. רבי ישמעאל ברבי אלישע
Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Elisha was a כהן, kohen, so he got the
first, he was to be given the first shearings of the sheep.
So somebody brought him these first shearings. Now, he had, you know,
he didn't have to give it to him because he could have
given it to any כהן. kohen. אמר ליה amar lei מהיכא את,
meiheicha at, where are you from? אמר ליה amar lei מדוך פלן
miduch pelan from such and such a place. ומהתם להכא umeihasam lehacha
לא הוה כהנא למיתבי ליה? lo havay kahana lemeisiv lei? I don't
get it. That's a hundred miles from here. You couldn't, you didn't
bump into one כהן kohen between there and here? אמר ליה amar
lei no, דינא אית לי, dina it li, you know what, because
I have a court case coming up, ואמינא ve'amina אגב אורחאי agav
orchai אייתי ליה למר. ayti lei lemar. Yeah, but I figured I
was coming here to this city anyway so I might as well
give it to you. So again notice in all these cases they
explicitly mention they have a court case coming up. אמר ליה: Amar
lei: פסילנא לך לדינא. Psilna lach ledina. You've invalidated me to be
a judge for you. לא קביל מיניה. Lo kabil minei. He didn't
accept. Now notice by the way, even though he withdrew, he recused
himself, not only did he recuse himself, he also didn't accept the
gift, right, in both cases. So okay, לא קביל מיניה. Lo kabil
minei. אוסיב ביה זוגא דרבנן. Oisiv bei zuga derabbanan. So he gave
him two other rabbis to judge the case. וקדייני ליה. Vkadainei lei.
And they were judging him. בהדי דקאזיל ואתי. Bahadi dka'azil va'ati. While
they were going, he's going back and forth. אמר. Amar: He was
saying, same story, אי בעיתון הכי, אי בעיתון הכי. Ei baisun hachi,
ei baisun hachi. If he argues this way, if he argues this
way, he could pay this, he could pay this. Why isn't he
arguing this way? אמר: תיפח נפשם שמקבלי שוחד. Tipach nafsham shemekablei shochad.
Blast be the souls of those who accept bribes. ומה אני שלא
נטלתי ואם נטלתי שלי נטלתי. Umah ani shelo natalti ve'im natalti sheli
natalti. I didn't accept, and had I done it, it would have
been, would literally have been his, the same way the other thing
would have been literally the guy's fruit, but here anyway, I would
have been entitled to get it because I was a כהן. kohen.
מקבלי שוחד אחת כמה וכמה. Mekablei shochad achas kamah vechamah. How much
more so those who accept שוחד. Okay, I guess we should end
here. All right, so continue this tomorrow. Yes? What if you knew
a particular judge was very tough, so you offered him something so
that he would disqualify himself? Yeah, that's true. You could try, I
mean, if you're smart, you could try to get certain judges to
recuse themselves. One of the topics of course, judge shopping. Well...